<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God's holy name magnified, and his truth exalted by the testimony of his faithful servants who have suffered the cruel penalty of banishment from their native country by the rulers thereof as also an abstract of their names : with some of the barbarous dealings and useages they received and sustained from the hands of those instruments that were imployed in the imbarquing of them / R.C. Unto which is annexed Englands sad estate and condition lamented / written by George Fox the younger in the beginning of the year 1661 ...</title>
            <author>R. C. (Richard Crane)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08495675</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08495675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41404</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34915)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41404)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1253:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God's holy name magnified, and his truth exalted by the testimony of his faithful servants who have suffered the cruel penalty of banishment from their native country by the rulers thereof as also an abstract of their names : with some of the barbarous dealings and useages they received and sustained from the hands of those instruments that were imployed in the imbarquing of them / R.C. Unto which is annexed Englands sad estate and condition lamented / written by George Fox the younger in the beginning of the year 1661 ...</title>
                  <author>R. C. (Richard Crane)</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, d. 1661. Englands sad estate and condition lamented.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41404:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41404:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD'S holy Name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> AND HIS TRUTH EXALTED BY THE Teſtimony of his Faithful Servants who have ſuffered the Cruel Penalty of BANISHMENT from their Native Country by the RULERS thereof: <hi>AS ALSO</hi> An ABSTRACT of their Names, with ſome of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Dealings and Uſeages they received and ſuſtained from the hands of thoſe Inſtruments that were imployed in the Imbarquing of them. R.C.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Doth not the Teares run down the Widdowes Cheeks, and her Cry is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him that cauſed them, for from her Cheeks do they go up unto Heaven, and the Lord which heareth them doth accept them, and the Lord will not be ſlack, nor the Almighty will not tarry long from them, till he hath ſmitten in ſunder the loynes of the unmercifull, and aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelf of the Heathen, till he have taken away the multitudes of the Cruell, and broken the Scepter of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous, till he give every Man after his works, and reward them after their devices, till he have judged the Cauſe of his People, and comforted them with his mercies, <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſticus 35.</hi> ver. <hi>15.</hi> &amp; <hi>18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>They are <hi>Abrahams</hi> Children who are of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith; who forſook his native Country, Fathers houſe, and his own Kindred, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord he knew not whither, <bibl>Gal. <hi>3.7.</hi> Gen. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>And they are of <hi>Cains</hi> ſeed who are found in <hi>Cains</hi> nature, who ſlew his Brother becauſe his own works were evil and his Brother's Righteous, <bibl>
                     <hi>1</hi> John <hi>3.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Unto which is annexed <hi>Englands</hi> ſad eſtate and condition lamented. (Written by <hi>George Fox</hi> the younger, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the year 1661.) In which are ſome Propheſies that now are fulfilled and fulfilling.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41404:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41404:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIEND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou that reads this enſuing <hi>Relation,</hi> will find what hath been diſpenced to us from the hands of the men of this Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as thy mind is kept cool out of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, thou wilt alſo be able to judge in thy meaſure concerning our ſufferings, as to our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves we are well ſatisfied, and in the will of God do reſt and acquieſce: But to ſatisfie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who deſire to be informed, this <hi>Relation</hi> is wrote, and alſo in order to Record, and the reaſon why it is ſo ſuddenly brought forth, is, becauſe the Mortality of <hi>Mankind is great in this City,</hi> where theſe things have been done and committed, and <hi>eternity</hi> preſſeth ſore on this Generation, and a remiſneſs herein might make void the record of our teſtimony, which Record will have a place, amongst all the faithful witneſſes of God, for his holy truth
<pb facs="tcp:41404:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> every Generation to this day, and the very end of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> according the actions of men in their ſeveral Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, is for the benefit of their <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> and undoubted the next Generation muſt judge the works of their <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> &amp; think it not ſtrange we receive ſuch hard meaſure from the hands of the Rulers of this Nation, for the holy record of Scriptures are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled on this Generation, which ſaith, <hi>They ſhall hale you before Magiſtrates, and they ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon you; and whoſoever ſhall kill you ſhall think he doth God good ſervice:</hi> And he who ſpake forth theſe words ſuffered from the ſame ſeed that miniſters our ſufferings unto us; which ſeed is one, even from the begining to this day, there are but two, the <hi>perſecuting ſeed,</hi> and the <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeed,</hi> and theſe are known by their fruits, <hi>For, Grapes are not gathered of Thorns, nor Figgs upon Thiſtles:</hi> And our ſufferings have been mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed very much ſince the return of this Power, &amp; heightened even to <hi>BANISHMENT,</hi> which is more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere then death it ſelf, the Lord permiting it ſo to be we are content; though I muſt tell thee, as we are a people and a conſiderable one in <hi>England,</hi> our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and promiſes from <hi>BREDA,</hi> and ſince ſo often repeated, was neither <hi>Impriſonment</hi> nor <hi>Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but theſe things with our juſt cauſe we leave to the Righteous God to judge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41404:3"/>
            <head>God's holy Name magnified, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>PErſecution in the World is no new thing, for ſuch as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts a holy and blameleſs life, in that Generation in which they are brought forth, doth aſſuredly meet with it, and it hath been the practiſe in every Generation, from <hi>Caine</hi> downward, and all in his nature, even to this day, to Perſecute God in his appearance, in his Servants and Saints, as is plentifully ſeen and made known in this our day, and Generation, which is the product of this <hi>Relation,</hi> and the <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> have been, and are they that act theſe <hi>Cruelties</hi> upon God's holy Saints, the <hi>Prieſt</hi> with Tongue, the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> with Fiſt, and ſo is <hi>Perſecution</hi> brought forth; and between theſe two, are, and have been all the <hi>Rapes, Spoyles, Injuries, Impriſonments, Deaths, Baniſhments,</hi> and all manner of cruel exerciſes inflicted upon the People of the Lord for their Conſciences to him, and in every Generation <hi>Perſecution</hi> hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manifeſtation of God, been leſs or more exerciſed; For this is infallible, <hi>the greater appearance of God in Fleſh, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Perſecution, raiſed by the Devil in Fleſh,</hi> and here is the miſtery of the two Seeds ſhewed, and each Seed beares its Fathers Image, and ſo they come to be known, and <hi>eternal</hi> enmity is placed between them, therefore the holy Witneſſes for God in every Generation, have ſuſtained more or leſs of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> according as is ſaid, to the manifeſtation and appearance of God in them, raiſed up and held forth in Teſtimony unto the World, and as this appearance of God comes to be lived in and unto, then the World is teſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, <hi>that the deeds thereof are evil;</hi> And here firſt begins <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and thoſe that perſevere in faithfulneſs unto what God hath manifeſted, they meet with ſuch meaſure from <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as is hereafter declared and we the People of God, called <hi>Quakers</hi> have by Gods permiſſion felt the weight of their perſecuting hands this many years, even ever ſince the Lord hath called us forth to teſtify unto his truth in this Nation, and our ſufferings have both abounded and multiplyed in theſe few years paſt: and as ſufferings
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41404:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abounded, ſo hath the love of God increaſed unto us; we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> living Witneſſes of it, praiſes, praiſes unto our God for ever, and we have a Witneſs for God in every <hi>Perſecuter's</hi> Conſcience in <hi>England</hi> of what rank or quality ſoever, that our ſufferings are not neither have been for evil doing, for if by their Provocations, they could have drawn us forth to have retaliated unto them in the ſame ſpirit the meaſure unto us, they had gotten their ends, but O the admired patience that God hath indued his People with, in that his mercy hath preſerved us from ſtaining our hands, with ſuch <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted works,</hi> and ſo our ſufferings are and have been on the Lord's account, from the beginning even to this very day, and as to our <hi>Impriſonments</hi> of ſundry kinds, and the <hi>Injury</hi> we have ſuſtained thereby is at this time omited, becauſe a <hi>Relation</hi> of the uſeage of my friends and brethren which did befall them from <hi>Newgate</hi> to their <hi>Ships</hi> into which they were drove for <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> after their long <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> in that <hi>Jaques</hi> or ſtinking <hi>Cell</hi> in which they were held, is the thing intended at this time.</p>
            <p>And the firſt that entred the Liſt of this <hi>Conflict</hi> and ſore Trial for their holy Teſtimonies, are theſe three Worthyes of the Lord, <hi>Edward Bruſh, Robert Hayes,</hi> and <hi>James Harding,</hi> who on the 24th of the <hi>Month,</hi> called <hi>March</hi> 6 5/4. was very betimes in the morning without any warning ſcarce given unto them, hurried down to <hi>Black Friers Staires</hi> by ſome of the <hi>Serviles</hi> of <hi>Newgate,</hi> where they were put into a <hi>Boate,</hi> and ſo rowed down to <hi>Graves end,</hi> and there they were forced on Board for <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> the former of which was very aged, and his grey Haires might have wrought com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in the hearts of his <hi>Perſecuters,</hi> beſides the teſtimony of his life amongſt whom he <hi>lived,</hi> for he was well known to ſome <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in this place, but the Lord hath drawn out his life unto this time, and God hath honoured him in his old age, to ſcale his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony unto his truth, by <hi>Cruell Baniſhment,</hi> who for his ſake only and alone left <hi>Wife, Child, Eſtate,</hi> and what ever was neer and deer unto him: The ſecond was <hi>Robert Hayes,</hi> as aboveſaid, who being taken out of the Priſon having received no ſuſtenance, and his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being very weak, he until that very morning having been in a Courſe of <hi>purging Phyſick,</hi> and for any thing I know it might not have done operating with him, was in this Caſe carried forth upon the Water, and the morning being exceeding cold, and no refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment afforded unto him between that and <hi>Graves end,</hi> within a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41404:4"/>
ſhort time after he was forced a board, he dyed, and his body was brought up to <hi>London</hi> which was interred amongſt his Brethren, and ſo he ſealed his Teſtimony for God's Truth, with his blood and his name is added to the number of the <hi>ſlaughtered Sheep of God</hi> in this Generation, who have been ſlain in <hi>England,</hi> he was a Man as to his yeares, and according to natures courſe, (had it not as I may ſay been for that <hi>inhumane</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> uſeage he ſuſtained) that might have lived many yeares; So deer <hi>Edward Bruſh,</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion in Tribulation, <hi>James Harding</hi> was the firſt in <hi>England</hi> that have taſted the fruit of <hi>exile</hi> from their native Land in which they were born, and out of that <hi>City</hi> in which their <hi>Privileges</hi> and <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes</hi> are as <hi>ample</hi> as the <hi>Chief Magiſtrate</hi> himſelf, (ſetting his Office aſide) but this we know, that <hi>Pretious in the ſight of God are the death of his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus hath God ſuffer'd theſe things to befall theſe three faithful ſervants of his, in whom his Name is magnified, and his truth exalted, Praiſes, praiſes, living praiſes to him be given for ever: Yet nevertheleſs, God who loved them, was not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he viſited this <hi>City</hi> with a rebuke, and that they might take notice of it, within a few doors of that faithful Man's houſe <hi>E. B.</hi> a houſe was ſhut up (as was ſaid) of the <hi>Plague,</hi> and indeed it was the firſt that I ever heard of in the <hi>City;</hi> ſo <hi>the preſident of your wrath, was attended with an example of judgment, and that from the hand of the Lord;</hi> and an entrance being made into this work, not withſtanding the <hi>wrath</hi> and fury of the Lord did hang over this <hi>City</hi> like a Cloud over-burdened with rain, and ready to pour forth; and having by cruel threats overcome the <hi>Shipmaſters</hi> to make them the Executioners of their cruel edict or Law, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this advantage by an <hi>Embargoe</hi> laid upon all <hi>Merchants Ships</hi> out-bound, except a paſs from under the hand of the <hi>Admiral</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, none might paſs forth of the <hi>River;</hi> and many <hi>Shipmaſters</hi> having layn long in hopes of an accompliſhment of their intended Voyages, were now fruſtrate, for a paſs they muſt go, and that would not be granted, except they would embarqueſome <hi>Quakers</hi> aboard, each of them to be ſcattered into the ſeveral <hi>Iſlands,</hi> into which they were bound, and though ſeveral of the <hi>Shipmaſters</hi> did withſtand the thing, uſing many good Arguments to avoid the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the cruel penalty, urging the Law made, commanded not them, and that there is a Law in <hi>England</hi> unrepealed that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibites
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41404:5"/>
the tranſporting of any perſon out of this Nation without his or her proper conſent; and as ſome of theſe <hi>Shipmaſters</hi> knows and have been given to know, the laſt <hi>executive Officer</hi> is the <hi>Sheriffe,</hi> and that he is to <hi>contract</hi> with any <hi>Shipmaſter</hi> for their <hi>Tranſportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> but I find not in the Law that the <hi>Sheriffe</hi> hath power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell any man to bargain with him, no more than any Tradeſman hath power to compell any <hi>Chapman</hi> whatever to buy or ſell with him; the <hi>Shipmaſter</hi> is left free in all and every ſuch caſe, but all theſe things muſt not ſerve, the ſervants of the Lord muſt be <hi>baniſhed,</hi> and they muſt carry them, (law or not law) elſe they muſt looſe their Voyages, the <hi>Rulers</hi> wills muſt be done, and where a <hi>defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> in Law is, or that it anſwer not fully their ends, then high words, and threatning ſpeeches of <hi>impriſonment,</hi> and the like, muſt anſwer all defects; and ſo having wrought upon the <hi>extremities</hi> of theſe men, and they having conſulted their loſſes, if they anſwer not <hi>their</hi> wills, and alſo having reſpect to their private gain, more then anſwering a good Conſcience to God, an agreement is made, and ſo comes the <hi>ſervants</hi> of the Lord, to be <hi>baniſhed</hi> from their native Country; the great God permitting it ſo to be: and have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come over the <hi>Shipmaſters</hi> as is ſaid; again they enterprize the ſending of ſeven more of the ſervants of the moſt High into <hi>Exile,</hi> and upon the 18. of the 2d. <hi>month</hi> 1665. was it ſuffered to be done; (and by the <hi>ſerviles</hi> of <hi>Newgate,</hi> whoſe deligence in thoſe things have been long experienced,) their Names are, <hi>Tho. Gibſon, John Tyſce, John Terry, Edward Maletrat, John Goodwin, John Hardin, Edward Boycot:</hi> and from the Priſon in the morning were ſix of there faithful Servants of the Lord drove down and led by the <hi>Newgate Inſtruments</hi> unto <hi>Black-fryars Stairs,</hi> where a <hi>Barge</hi> was ready to receive them, which was accordingly done; but <hi>Thomas Gibſon</hi> refuſing to yield an <hi>active complyance</hi> unto them, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a <hi>Coach,</hi> and ſo fetched him out of Priſon into it, and carried him down to <hi>Tower-Wharfe,</hi> where the <hi>Barge</hi> waited to receive him, and ſo he was put into the <hi>Barge</hi> amongſt his Brethren, who were from thence carried to <hi>Graveſend</hi> and forced aboard in order to their <hi>Baniſhment.</hi> And dear <hi>Thomas Gibſon</hi> whoſe life with the reſt, and their faithfulneſs in their teſtimonies unto Gods living truth will be a pretious ſavour in Generations to come; and when their lives and ſufferings with all their tryals, and faithfulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in comes to be read and compared with the meaſure they have met
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41404:5"/>
withal, and received from their <hi>Perſecuters</hi> of this Generation in which they lived, and did the will of God, ſurely, ſurely, praiſes, praiſes will be given unto God, by them that are yet unborn, and will bleſs God for this day; and ſo theſe <hi>ſeven</hi> faithful Lambs are gone by the permiſſion of God into <hi>exile,</hi> and have for truths ſake parted with Wives, Children, and Eſtates, to fulfill the Holy will of God who is bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <p>Not many dayes after the embarquing of theſe faithful Brethren, the Lord ſhewed another notable example by cuting off that <hi>grand Inſtrument Iudge Hyde</hi> by ſudden death; who the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wrought much, yea very much of our <hi>detriment,</hi> both in our <hi>impriſonments,</hi> our <hi>tryals,</hi> and in <hi>expediating</hi> our <hi>Baniſhment:</hi> But he is gone to his place, and the fruits of the deeds in his life, is his food to <hi>eternity;</hi> and ſo I ſhall not particularize his ſeveral carriages to us in our <hi>impriſonments</hi> and <hi>tryals;</hi> but leave it to others to read over the lines of his life, which is written with <hi>a point of an Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant:</hi> And about that time the Lord began to pour out his <hi>plagues</hi> in ſome of the out parts of the <hi>City,</hi> and then <hi>Weekly-bills</hi> began to declare the <hi>Judgements of a juſt God,</hi> and in a manner, as in his fear I may ſpeak it, as they began to <hi>baniſh</hi> in ſmall numbers, firſt 3. then 7. and afterwards greater numbers, as may by and by be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared; even ſo hath the <hi>Judgments</hi> of God <hi>traced</hi> that <hi>malicious ſpirit,</hi> firſt in ſmall numbers and ſo with greater, as any that will make the obſervation upon the <hi>weekly-bills</hi> of <hi>Mortality</hi> may find it ſo; <hi>juſt and righteous O dreadful God are thy judgments, who haſt judged thus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not many weeks paſſed, but another experiment muſt be made, by ſending away for <hi>Baniſhment</hi> now <hi>eight,</hi> malice encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing one in number, the Names of theſe faithful innocent Lambs are <hi>Rob. Allin, Tho. Kent, John Raunce, Tho. Hodg, Tho. Robins, John Johnſon, Tho. Parker, Rich. Poulton;</hi> all which were on the 26. of the 3d. <hi>month</hi> 1665. by thoſe <hi>emeſaries</hi> of <hi>Newgate</hi> forced out of Priſon and carried to the old place <hi>Black-fryars Stairs,</hi> and there was a <hi>Barge</hi> prepared for them, into which they were pulled, and ſo from thence to <hi>Graveſend</hi> were carried, where they were by <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> put aboard in order to <hi>baniſhment,</hi> and after ſome dayes lying in the <hi>River</hi> they were cleared at the <hi>Blockhouſe,</hi> which would not be done till the <hi>Shipmaſter</hi> made appear to the <hi>Searchers</hi> that he had the <hi>Quakers</hi> aboard, and ſo in the will of God, have theſe all born
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41404:6"/>
a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>thful teſtimony unto Gods holy truth, and have ſet their ſeales unto it, by giving up freely both Wives, Children, and their all; and rather then tranſgreſs the way of God, have choſen to receive their lots with their Brethren into what place ſoever the Lord ſhall permit them to be caſt, and have committed the truth of their cauſe unto a juſt God, who is now come to plead their <hi>innocency,</hi> with their and his adverſaries; <hi>and he will render vengeance upon the heads of them, and will ſmite hip and thigh, the whole hoſt of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed;</hi> and they ſhall know by his Judgments he is God and not another, and though theſe ſimple ſheep when before your <hi>Courts of judgment</hi> (ſo called) might not have liberty to plead the truth of their cauſe unto you, but with <hi>ironical, ſcoffing, jeering,</hi> and <hi>taunting</hi> language, have <hi>diſpenced your wills</hi> unto them, which is reckoned by you <hi>good law,</hi> but the righteous Judge hath looked down and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held all theſe things; and when any one have but ſpoken a <hi>ſentence</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> in defence of their juſt cauſe, you have <hi>retorted</hi> unto them theſe <hi>unſavory, ungodly, unchriſtianlike</hi> ſayings, <hi>hold your canting ſirrah, hold your canting ſirrah;</hi> I, even I have been both eye and ear witneſs of theſe things, even to the grief of my very <hi>ſoul,</hi> that ever men that ſhould ſit in Court to execute the Lawes of this <hi>Nation</hi> ſhould drop ſuch expreſſions from their mouths; and in publique. But what ſhall I ſay, in an acceptable time is the Lord ariſen to plead with the men of this Generation, when I have heard ſuch language given by <hi>old grey hair'd men,</hi> that hath ſate there to <hi>judge,</hi> I have ſaid in my heart, <hi>where are we arrived in this day; what, the Scriptures of truth called canting,</hi> a language learned under <hi>Hedges</hi> by <hi>Rogues</hi> and <hi>Vagabonds,</hi> ah woe is me, is this the <hi>reverence</hi> you have to the <hi>holy record</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> to call it <hi>canting,</hi> and in your <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature?</hi> ah miſerable men, what an example is this to them that comes to hear your wiſdoms; and may not young men by your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, turn meer <hi>heathen</hi> and <hi>atheiſts;</hi> but the Lord will awaken you, yea he will awaken you, to the confeſſion of him, and likewiſe that Records of truth ſpoken forth through his Servants by the Spirit of God, in their day and Generation, who received ſuch meaſure from the <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> then in being, as we now do from you in this <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now I return unto my <hi>Relation</hi> to obſerve the dealings with my Brethren and Siſters in the <hi>peſtiferous Jakes</hi> and <hi>Priſon</hi> of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> well, though notwithſtanding the fury of the Lord ſmoaks, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41404:6"/>
this <hi>City,</hi> and his wrath is come up <hi>to the</hi> number <hi>Thouſands,</hi> and he is cuting off in all parts, and his Judgments have even circum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered and beleagured it, and ſeeing it is the will of the Lord it ſhall be ſo; what ſaith the envious ſpirit, I <hi>will double and treble the number of thoſe that are under my hand and will drive them into <hi>exile;</hi>
               </hi> and in order thereunto a <hi>Shipmaſter</hi> a fit <hi>ſervile</hi> for ſuch an employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is found, who as it is ſaid of him, will <hi>baniſh</hi> his neereſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations for moneys; and a contract is drove with him, for <hi>no leſs</hi> then 60. innocent men and women, or thereabouts, to receive them into his <hi>Ship,</hi> to diſpoſe of them whetherto he is bound, and there to leave them to ſtarve and periſh; <hi>O mercyleſs Rulers, is this your Retaliation for the return out of your diſtreſs, the Lord if it be his will ſhew you more mercy then you ſhew unto his people;</hi> and a day is ordered for the diſpatching of this poor flock away out of their Country, and ſo as aforeſaid, in a morning with very ſhort warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was theſe friends about ſome 56. or 58. by the old <hi>ſerviles</hi> of <hi>Newgate</hi> taken forth and carried down to the ſame place, by 10.8. and ſometimes more in a company through the ſtreets, ſome drove and ſome led to the Waterſide untill they had got the number ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into the <hi>Barge</hi> prepared for them, and ſo away they were row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down to a place called <hi>Bugbeys Hole</hi> beyond <hi>Greenwich,</hi> where the <hi>Ship</hi> rode, and when they came unto the <hi>Ship</hi> theſe Inſtruments of <hi>Newgate</hi> did not find all things ſo ready to their hands, nor they in the Ship ſo willing as themſelves were, to do their maſters drud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery; the Seamen being ſome of them more conſiderate, refuſed to lay hands on them except they were willing; and theſe poor ſheep declared their unwillingneſs to yield any <hi>active complyance</hi> unto them; ſo a great <hi>buſle,</hi> and <hi>hurly burly</hi> was made, and many words uſed, <hi>magiſtrate like,</hi> by ſome of the <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> there, yet for all that, cared not the Seamen; ſo there was a cry to hand out the <hi>Tekel</hi> to hoiſt them up, and anſwer was made as I heard, <hi>that if they were Merchants Goods, they would do ſo;</hi> Anſwer was given again, <hi>they were the Kings Goods:</hi> But in the end, the <hi>Newgate</hi> ſervants was faine to fall to work, and <hi>with</hi> much ado they got four of this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber aboard, and then being tyred, the reſt were let alone, and after ſometime was returned to <hi>Newgate</hi> again, where they for ſometime was kept Priſoners. This was done the 20. day of the 5th. Month call'd <hi>July</hi> 1665. yet notwithſtanding all this and the return of theſe innocent perſons to their old Habitation, in which many of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41404:7"/>
our dear Friends have loſt their lives <hi>through the mercies of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of this Generation, which are altogether cruelties;</hi> and theſe things related, are tokens and marks of them, eaſie to be read of all that fear the Lord, and have any bowells of tenderneſs in them; and when they were there, ſafe they were, untill the envious ſpirit got another opportunity, which with ſome ſmall induſtry was purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and now ſeeing, the <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of <hi>Newgate</hi> could not effect their work, recourſe was had unto the <hi>Military power,</hi> and ſo a company of <hi>Redcoats</hi> muſt execute this <hi>barbarity,</hi> I have known a day when your very ſelves <hi>O Rulers,</hi> have cryed out upon <hi>Redcoat law;</hi> but that is forgot with you now, it ſeems you think fit it ſhould be miniſtred unto us, God Omnipotent judge between us and you in this matter, and ſo things being thus ordered, and the Lord permitting them ſo to be; a day was appointed, which was on the 4th. <hi>day</hi> of the 6th. <hi>month</hi> called <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1665. <hi>O malice,</hi> thou <hi>Monſter,</hi> will nothing <hi>ſatisfie but the ſlaughter of the Soul, through betraying the life of God by bowing and falling down to thee, or the death of the body, Lord thy will be done, and to do thy will, are we freely given up, either to live or to die, ſo thou be'ſt honoured Holy Father, thy name <hi>magnified,</hi> and thy truth <hi>exalted,</hi> above all <hi>deceipt, hypocriſie,</hi> and all manner of <hi>prophaneneſs:</hi>
               </hi> And in the morning early great was the preparation, and all or moſt that belonged to <hi>Newgate</hi> that could either lay hand of <hi>arme</hi> or <hi>leg</hi> was ſummoned to help to get this poor flock a <hi>Shipboard,</hi> and to their work they went, and as uſually they did, ſo now; ſome they led, ſome they drove in numbers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the drivers thought beſt for their eaſe, and thus they got them to the Waterſide, and into the <hi>Barge;</hi> and this in the face of the <hi>City,</hi> in whoſe ſtreets the <hi>bills</hi> of <hi>Mortality</hi> were the day before handed that ſignified the <hi>cuting off by death</hi> 3014. and ſo as they have encreaſed the numbers for <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> the Lord hath increaſed his <hi>Plagues</hi> amongſt them; and this <hi>O thou ſinful City, thou wilt both obſerve and conſider in time;</hi> and thoſe faithful ſouls were from thence rowed again to the ſame <hi>Ship</hi> to <hi>Bugby's-Hole</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and many Friends did accompany them to the <hi>Shipſide</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Boats,</hi> and after <hi>the Barge</hi> a couple of men belonging to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> follows in <hi>Boats,</hi> having <hi>Souldiers</hi> with them, which I ſuppoſe they purchaſed at the <hi>Tower</hi> to <hi>perpetrate</hi> that wicked work in hand; our <hi>Boats</hi> lying near the <hi>Ship,</hi> an out-cry was made by one of them, <hi>get you further from the Ship, or elſe we will ſink you;</hi> but Friends regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41404:7"/>
not what they ſaid, but lay ſtil keeping as ne'r the <hi>ſhip</hi> as they could. So theſe two <hi>Newgate Champions</hi> entring the <hi>Ship</hi> with their <hi>armed Men</hi> commanded by a <hi>Sarjeant</hi> or <hi>Coporal</hi> or ſome ſuch fellow, it matters not what; his demenour ſhewed himſelf to be a <hi>Bruit,</hi> and having made way in the <hi>Ship</hi> the Seamen were called, but few or none would lay hand on them, only two or three <hi>Vaſſals</hi> that were hired to help for that piece of ſervice, did ſhew themſelves as they were; ſo they placed themſelves for the conveniency of their work, then the <hi>Souldiers</hi> deſcended into the <hi>Barge</hi> and began to lay hold on Friends, and <hi>draged</hi> them forward, and ſome they <hi>kickt</hi> and <hi>punch'd,</hi> and heaved up many by <hi>Legs</hi> and <hi>Arms,</hi> and ſome they drew up with Ropes faſtened about their middles, like pieces of Timber, and ſo tumbled them into the <hi>Ship,</hi> and thus in an hours time or thereabout they had finiſhed their work, they ſerved <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> all alike, either lifted them up by <hi>violence</hi> or hoiſted them up by <hi>tekell,</hi> and thoſe two above mentioned, ſtanding in the waſt of the Ship, gave directions and orders, and well pleaſed they were in that <hi>diſmal ſight</hi> to ſee Men drawn up like Cattle, and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly they were obſerved to ſay, <hi>hand out the tackle to draw up the Kings goods,</hi> and <hi>take in the Kings goods,</hi> and this was their game and paſtime, they made over the bodies of theſe Servants of the Lord, the ſight of which cauſed exceeding grief in Friends who were Spectators of this <hi>Tragedy</hi> lying by the Ship ſide, O wofull wretches that ſport your ſelves in ſuch <hi>Inhumanities,</hi> as was there exerciſed, for you <hi>two</hi> above all the reſt of <hi>Newgate Inſtruments,</hi> you ſhould not have ſported your ſelves in that manner, for its known to you that <hi>when profeſſion in the Congregated way was in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion,</hi> you were for none of this work, and when <hi>one</hi> of you was a <hi>Diſciple</hi> of <hi>Parſon Griffith</hi> then none of this, but <hi>the Hypocrite God will judge and recompence with his juſt <hi>Plagues</hi> as well as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,</hi> and thus was this great piece of wicked work, finiſhed by the Inſtruments aboveſaid, and ſo are theſe Servants of the moſt High expoſed to cruel <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> having left behind them a good report for their faithfulneſs to the Lord, and a good favour is their Teſtimony for God's Truth unto all that have any ſence of him in them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41404:8"/>The Names of thoſe Friends laſt <hi>Baniſhed</hi> both Men and Women, being in number 55. are,
<list>
                  <head>VIZ,</head>
                  <item>Men Friends,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Peter Pennington.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Henry Tayler.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Hubbert.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Roger Roberts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edmund Berkley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Mathews.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Digory Marſhall.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Vincent Gerrard.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Noble.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nathaniel Harding.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Parker.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Roſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lawrence Aplin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Francis Terſey.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Cox.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Manaſſes Howard.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Chaplin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Clauſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Newman.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Robert Pate.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Lawrence Fullove.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>James Pierce.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Tillet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chriſtopher Dickeſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Fox.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Stoaks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Clark.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Bartholomew Hall.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Richard Thomſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>James Kirton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edward Walker.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Gabb.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Horſey.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Matthew Jackson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edward Lee.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Arthur Baker.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Roberts.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Women Friends,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Deborah Harding.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Anne Prieſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Elizabeth Ivers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Anne Horniblow.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Roſe Atkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Elizabeth Fiſher.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Anne Mercer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Jane Powell.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mary Middleton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rachel Jackson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chriſtian Ford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Elizabeth Pike.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Elizabeth Harding.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Rebecka Trump.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Anne Royley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dorothy Hall.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Patience Willſon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Margaret Jackson.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Baniſh'd in all 72. remains in Priſon ſentenced for Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about 72.</p>
            <p>And theſe are part of thoſe <hi>inhumane uſuages</hi> which the people of the Lord (who are by <hi>violence</hi> drove out of their native Country into <hi>exile</hi>) have ſuſtained and received from the hands of their <hi>Rulers,</hi> and thoſe inſtruments that are imployed in the execution of their Law laſt made for that purpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the progreſs of thirteen months or upward, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of it; and it is little
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41404:8"/>
taken notice of by our <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> how many <hi>Widdows</hi> and <hi>father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Children</hi> they have made by this their cruel work in this time; But now the Lord is <hi>retaliating</hi> into their boſomes, and is meaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto you, as you have meaſured unto us, and many <hi>widdows</hi> and <hi>fatherleſs</hi> will he make, for our ſakes, yea for our ſakes; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not deceived, our innocency is aſſuredly come before the Lord, and our cryes are heard, and he is recompencing of your works into your hands that you have wrought theſe many years; and what will you ſay, it is the <hi>great God</hi> that pleads with you; O <hi>London, London,</hi> thou maiſt remember a few years ſince thou was ſporting thy ſelf and making merry, thy <hi>Inhabitants</hi> was even <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted</hi> with vain joy; Remember thy waſting of Gods good Creatures, upon thy <hi>luſt</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi> thy <hi>Bonfires,</hi> thy <hi>Roſteing of good meat in the ſtreet, and baſting it with kenel dirt and water;</hi> the worſt morſel of which, thouſands and ten thouſands would be glad of, and many for want of theſe things periſh now; and remember thy <hi>vain ſhews erected in the high places of thee,</hi> when no leſs then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 600. <hi>of the ſervants of the Lord were in priſon</hi> in and about thee, looking through the <hi>Grates</hi> of thy <hi>Priſons,</hi> and even panting for very air: In that very day the ſervants of the Lord did bear that burthen of all your ungodlineſs, under which many walked up and down more like to <hi>ſhadowes</hi> then <hi>men,</hi> even to ſee what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of your wayes, in which you were <hi>poſting</hi> and <hi>gadding</hi> like wild <hi>Cattle;</hi> what think you, was <hi>God ſerved</hi> therein, or the <hi>Devil?</hi> By this time many thouſands in thee are ſenſible of the provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wherewith you provoked the Lord in that day; but in all thoſe actions the mighty God beheld you, and alſo his ſervants who had done no injury to any of you at all; notwithſtanding that all muſt be cooped up in your <hi>Priſons,</hi> till you had offered your wicked <hi>heatheniſh ſacrifice</hi> unto your <hi>luſts</hi> in that day you were told by many of the day that hath now overtaken thee, <hi>O London,</hi> and thou did'ſt not believe it; but however now thou both ſeeſt it, and feeleſt it to be true, and now inſtead of healths which thou vainly drunk to men in thy <hi>Bowles</hi> and <hi>Cups, thou haſt</hi> ſickneſs from the hand of the Almighty; and inſtead of thy <hi>mad joy,</hi> thou haſt handed to thee a cup of <hi>deep ſorrow;</hi> and them thou <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ified</hi> O <hi>City</hi> in <hi>that day,</hi> and for whom theſe things were wrought, hath now left thee in the very middeſt of thy miſery. And now conſider <hi>O London,</hi> is it not better to truſt the Lord than man, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils; <hi>ſome
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41404:9"/>
put their truſt in Princes, ſome in Horſes, but it is good to truſt the Lord:</hi> and had'ſt thou conſidered this in thy former day, well had it been with thee; and as for thoſe that did help to promp on thy ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs in that day, thoſe they were that by their <hi>Oaths, execrations,</hi> and all abominable wretched practiſes, in <hi>whoring</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and what not; in their <hi>Feathers</hi> and <hi>ſtrange faſhions;</hi> have theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſhed thee alſo, it had been well thou hadſt never known them, but however this memorial they have left behind them, <hi>even their ſhameful ſpewings,</hi> yea their <hi>ſhameful ſpewings in every corner of thy Streets:</hi> And for all this the ſervants of the Lord undergoes more cruelties from <hi>Thee</hi> and thy <hi>Rulers</hi> then ever; what do ye account we were born and brought forth as Men and Women to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; was this the end the Lord gave us life for, think yee? and do you think it is our portion to ſpend our dayes in your <hi>Priſons?</hi> what, becauſe the thing hath been continued, and is common; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, you look upon it, it is but right it ſhould ſo be, and ſo from the <hi>Womb</hi> unto the <hi>Tomb,</hi> this is our portion from your hands.</p>
            <p>And thus we have been all along, and are made the very <hi>Prey</hi> of a company of <hi>Rapine fowle,</hi> and <hi>Fleſhcrowes,</hi> who <hi>teareth our fleſh from our bones, and drinks our bloods in your ſtinking Jakes</hi> and <hi>Priſons.</hi> But dear God, it is for thy dear truths ſake that we undergo theſe things from the Men of this Generation. O <hi>glorifie, glorifie</hi> thy ſelf holy Father in all theſe things that have been ſuffered to befall thy Saints and ſervants in this age, we know holy God it is becauſe they know not thee, they do theſe things unto thine, for did they know thee, they would fear thee, and if they did fear thee, then they would love thee; and if they did love thee, then would they love thine: Righteous God, becauſe they know not thee, therefore they know not us; for thou haſt made known thy ſelf in us, and ſo come we to bear thy Heavenly Image; O <hi>magnifie</hi> thy name <hi>great God,</hi> and let all confeſs unto thee, unto thy mercies, unto thy <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> unto thy Righteouſneſs; unto thy <hi>forbearance</hi> and <hi>mighty pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> unto thy <hi>loving kindneſs,</hi> unto thy <hi>truth,</hi> for thou art God moſt mighty, even God of Heaven and Earth, and there is none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee; in Earth or Heaven, the Gods of the Earth are not able to ſtand, in thy judgment. O powerful God make thy power more and more known amongſt the Sons and Daughters of Men, that they may learn thy fear; that <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>unbelief</hi> may be rooted up in this Nation, and that plant of ungodlineſs O Lord pluck up, by thy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41404:9"/>
mighty power that it be no more, and for thine holy God, who for thy truth ſake are drove into <hi>exile;</hi> let thy ſweet peace, which is a portion beyond utterance, anſwer all the wants they may in their body ſuſtain, and increaſe thy love in <hi>them,</hi> ſo will they love one another; and Righteous God be with all thine whom thou haſt gathered into thee either in bonds or at liberty, for all thine are one fleſh and one bone; in faithfulneſs let all perſevere, thy great name <hi>magnifie,</hi> O God exalt thy truth above all <hi>National inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which they frame and conſtitute unto thee (O ſpiritual God) for worſhip, thou art a Spirit, therefore by <hi>art</hi> thou art not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; and though men chuſeth it, and ordereſt it for thee, it is becauſe they know thee not; and imagines thee to be like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>inventions</hi> may pleaſe Men, but thou art not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with them, thou chuſeſt thy worſhip thy ſelf, thou ſeekeſt thy Worſhippers, holy God, out of all viſible things is thy Worſhip, in the inviſible thou art both known and ſeen, and all that comes to know thee and to ſee thee, muſt come into the inviſible, and when they come there then ſhall we be known of them as we are known of thee, and then no more <hi>Perſecution</hi> but <hi>Love,</hi> which is thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, which is thy expreſs Image, O mighty God honour thy Self, Glorify thy Self, Magnifie thy Self, and advance and exalt thy deer Truth over all, O thou art worthy of all praiſe from thee in thine, Bleſſed to Eternity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>NOtwithſtanding the ſore Calamity that is by the hand of a moſt righteous God inflicted upon this City, and that the laſt weeks Bill declared <hi>3014.</hi> yet for all this, and in this time they ſeized our Meeting in <hi>Joneſes</hi> at the <hi>Peele,</hi> and took away the moſt of Men friends, amounting to the number of about <hi>25.</hi> and carried them to be examined before <hi>George Monck,</hi> called <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Albema le,</hi> who after one nights been there their names being taken, but not being brought before him, was diſpoſed of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41404:10"/>
to Priſon, ſome to the <hi>Gate-houſe,</hi> and ſome to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where they remain Priſoners for the teſtimony of Gods holy Truth, and though they had ſent fifty five of the Servants of the Lord into cruel exile laſt week, as it were to make an experiment of theſe actions, and as I have heard it reported, that ſome ſhould ſay, that if the <hi>Quakers</hi> were ſent out of the Land, it would be the onely expedient of ſtopping the <hi>Plague,</hi> but behold what an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it hath wrought, and how the Lord hath dealt in this cauſe, that this week ſince this hath been done <hi>1016.</hi> is increaſed in the Judgement in this Bill, for no leſs then <hi>4030.</hi> is cut off which this Weeks Bill declares, and ſo ſuch Diviners, if it were ſo ſpoken by them, are falce and lyars, for they ſee a contrary effect, and thoſe that cauſeth theſe our cruel and unjuſt ſufferings, may well obſerve the hand of a retaliating God upon you, and except they intend to take vengeance upon the moſt High, I am yet to learn their intentions in this matter, O poor Mortals that thus ſtriveth againſt the God of Heaven, what ſhall I ſay, a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, a Lamentation, yea a bitter Lamentation is to be taken up for you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="complaint">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41404:10"/>
            <head>ENGLAND'S ſad Eſtate and Condition lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this juſt Complaint taken up againſt the greateſt part of her <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> Becauſe of their great <hi>Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> and <hi>Treacherous Dealings,</hi> both with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> For which cauſe the <hi>Terrible</hi> and <hi>Righteous Judgments</hi> of the Lord are coming upon them, and the Land.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein is alſo contained ſome <hi>PROPHESIES</hi> and <hi>EXHORTATIONS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OH ENGLAND, <hi>England!</hi> The <hi>Abominations</hi> of the greateſt part of thy <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> who can declare them! They have reached Heaven, ſo as they are come up before the Lord, the Jealous God, and <hi>Wo</hi> unto that part of thy <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> who have ſinned out the Day of their <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation,</hi> and have wholly ſlighted the Day of <hi>God's patience,</hi> and <hi>long Forbearance,</hi> and would have none of his <hi>Reproof,</hi> but have altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejected the ſame, and have made a mock at <hi>Sin,</hi> &amp; have ſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves with their own <hi>Deceivings</hi> and <hi>Luſts,</hi> and have gone a Whoring from under the God of their Lives: Wherefore thus ſaith the Lord, the onely God; <hi>I will make ſuch become a Hiſſing</hi> and <hi>Reproach, and my Anger they ſhall not be able to Eſcape, becauſe of their provoking Abominations,</hi> and <hi>Treacherous Dealings both with</hi> Me <hi>and</hi> Man.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> How have, and yet do, a great part of <hi>thy Inhabitants</hi> Ruſh into <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and all manner of <hi>Profaneſs</hi> and grievous <hi>Abominations,</hi> even as the <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Mighty</hi> Ruſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Battel! How do they drink in <hi>Iniquity</hi> even as the <hi>Ox,</hi> or <hi>Parched Ground,</hi> drinketh in Water! Oh! What manner of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> ſhall I make for thee, my <hi>Native Countrey!</hi> Or, What manner of <hi>Complaint</hi> may I take up againſt a great part of thine <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants,</hi> who have long Sought, and yet ſeek thy <hi>Ruine</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction!</hi> Verily, their Actions have Declared them to be like the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41404:11"/>
Inhabitants of <hi>Sodom;</hi> Yea, their ſins have rendred them to be as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d as thoſe of <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> O they have <hi>Vexed</hi> the Righteous Soul; Yea, and they have <hi>Grieved</hi> the Spirit of the Lord from <hi>Day</hi> to <hi>Day</hi> with their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Converſations.</hi> They have multiplied their <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,</hi> and heaped up their <hi>Iniquities</hi> till they are become as the Sand on the Sea-ſhore without Number. Oh! The Lord hath long ſtriven with them; yea, He hath alſo long born their <hi>Iniquities,</hi> He would have gathered them to himſelf out of their <hi>Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,</hi> Yea, he would oft have healed them, but they would not; but they have ſtiffned their Necks, and hardned their Hearts againſt the Lord and his Counſel day after day, and have choſen their own <hi>way</hi> and <hi>works</hi> even to their <hi>own hurt,</hi> and would by no means be reclaimed; for when the Lord hath reproved them (by the Light of his Son in their own conſciences) and ſet their ſins in order before their eyes, they have <hi>ſtopped</hi> their <hi>Eares,</hi> and <hi>cloſed</hi> their <hi>Eyes,</hi> and willfully Rebelled againſt the Power of God, and trampled upon his Witneſs [the Light in them] as a thing of nought, counting it not worth the taking Notice of. And when the Lord hath raiſed up <hi>Prophets, Children,</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> and ſent them out, Commanding them <hi>to lift up their Voyces like Trumpets, to ſhew the People their Tranſgreſſion, and to Preach Repentance and Amendment of Life:</hi> Yea, <hi>to warn and exhort them to turn from their Sins to God, and to lay before them their great abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and to Propheſie what ſhould come upon them, if they would not turn from the evil of their Doings.</hi> Oh! how have a great part of <hi>thy Inhabitants Scorned,</hi> and <hi>Derided</hi> theſe! Yea, how have many of <hi>thine Inhabitants Beaten, Whipt, Stock't, Stoned,</hi> and <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned</hi> ſome of theſe <hi>till Death,</hi> for bearing their Teſtimony for the Lord againſt <hi>a Crooked</hi> and <hi>Perverſe Generation,</hi> who <hi>hate</hi> ſuch as ſpeak <hi>uprightly,</hi> and <hi>abhor</hi> ſuch as <hi>reprove Sin</hi> in the Gate, that ſo it is even thus come to paſs in thee, <hi>O England, That he that departeth from Iniquity, maketh himſef a Prey</hi> to this Generation of <hi>Evil doers,</hi> whoſe hearts are ſet upon their <hi>Luſts, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>grievous Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations!</hi> and the Lord hath beheld it, and it pleaſeth him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is <hi>no true Judgment:</hi> for theſe evil doers are <hi>all</hi> gone out of the way; yea there is <hi>none</hi> of them that regard to do the thing that's <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> any further than it may be <hi>advantagious</hi> to their own <hi>Corrupt Deſignes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> How oft hath the Lord God ſmote <hi>thy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41404:11"/>
Rulers</hi> and <hi>Mighty,</hi> and <hi>Proud Men!</hi> how oft hath he laid their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Duſt! Yea, How oft hath he <hi>Overturned</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded</hi> thy <hi>Mighty Men,</hi> even thy <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> with thy <hi>Princes, Nobles,</hi> and <hi>Captaines</hi> of Thouſands, Hundreds and Fifties! Oh how oft hath he <hi>Overturned thy Governments,</hi> and <hi>Changed thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours!</hi> But how few of them have ſo <hi>regarded the Out-goings</hi> of the Lord in all theſe things as they ought to have done? And how few of them have rightly <hi>Weighed</hi> and <hi>Conſidered</hi> the Cauſes for which the Lord hath brought or ſuffered ſo many <hi>Changes</hi> in the Land? Or, have thoſe who ſaw the cauſes that provoked the Lord of hoſts thus to Act, laboured ſo to remove them as they ought to do (or might) have done? Nay, Aſſuredly they have not; for the <hi>Luſts</hi> of this World, and the <hi>Pride</hi> of Life hath blinded the minds of moſt; and ſuch who have ſeen what their duty was, the <hi>honour of this World,</hi> &amp; that curſed <hi>ſelf-intereſt</hi> hath ſtopped and hindred moſt of them from doing thoſe things which they ſaw they ought (and which they had opportunity alſo) to have done. Oh! How have the <hi>new Governors</hi> in almoſt every <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>late,</hi> cryed out of the <hi>Tirany</hi> and <hi>great Oppreſſion</hi> of thoſe whom they did ſucceed? and, how have moſt of them <hi>Vowed</hi> unto God, <hi>Declared</hi> to, and <hi>Promiſed</hi> the People, <hi>That they would Remove the Burdens and Oppreſſions that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Rulers had laid, and continued upon them:</hi> But <hi>alas!</hi> very few of them, have regarded <hi>their Vowes, Declarations, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> either <hi>to God</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> but in <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Deceit</hi> have they gone on, Serving themſelves and their own Luſts, and not the Lord nor their Generation faithfully: For, although many of them have been very <hi>large in promiſes</hi> and <hi>good words,</hi> (whereby they have long ſought to deceive the hearts of the People) yet it is but very <hi>Little</hi> that hath been done for their <hi>true Liberty,</hi> becauſe that wicked Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which ſeeketh to make it ſelf great by the ruine of others, hath <hi>Ruled,</hi> and doth yet <hi>Rule,</hi> in the hearts of many Rulers; and this is of the Devourer and Deſtroyer, who cannot <hi>forgive Enemies,</hi> but Crys out of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> labouring to exaſperate the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Others, that ſo occaſions may be gotten, if poſſible, againſt them, thereby to bring them under, and keep them in Bondage.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> Such is thy ſad <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Condition,</hi> that ſeverall of thy <hi>Rulers</hi> are, and have been, as <hi>roaring Lyons,</hi> even greedy to <hi>Devoure;</hi> And many of thy <hi>Teachers</hi> have been, and yet are, like <hi>Troops of Robbers,</hi> Robbing and Spoiling of many of thine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41404:12"/>
Inhabitants. Oh! How have moſt of thy <hi>Prieſts Temporized,</hi> and <hi>Daubed</hi> with every Power, as they have come up in the <hi>many Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges!</hi> How have they encreaſed <hi>Envy, Wars,</hi> and <hi>Deſtructions,</hi> amongſt thy <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>People!</hi> How have they <hi>one time Cryed up,</hi> and <hi>Prayed</hi> for the <hi>ſame Thing,</hi> which, at <hi>another time,</hi> they have <hi>Cryed down,</hi> and <hi>Prayed againſt!</hi> Oh! Who ſhall ever believe them? Their <hi>god</hi> is their <hi>belly;</hi> and who is it that many of them would not Joyn unto, if thereby they might be upheld in <hi>Pride, Idleneſs,</hi> and <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> How oft would they <hi>Change again and again?</hi> And what <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> is there that many of them would not Run into for their <hi>Bellies ſake?</hi> Ah poor Nation! Are they not yet ſtriving to kindle a Flame within thy Bowels? Hath not the Lord divided them? and, are they not labouring with all their might to <hi>Divide</hi> and <hi>Rend</hi> thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants yet <hi>more</hi> and <hi>more?</hi> Yea, ſurely, and it is Juſt with the Lord to ſuffer it to be ſo; becauſe of the greatneſs of their <hi>Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> which are daily encreaſed.</p>
            <p>Ah poor Land! How art thou overſpread with <hi>Waſters</hi> and <hi>ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers!</hi> who like <hi>Caterpillars</hi> devour thy <hi>Pleaſant Fruit.</hi> Oh! the <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> and <hi>Idolatries,</hi> that are daily committed and acted in thee, Who can Declare them! Oh! thy <hi>Chief City,</hi> thy <hi>Chief City,</hi> that <hi>bloody City!</hi> Can its <hi>Abominations</hi> be <hi>Parallel'd</hi> in the Earth! Surely it hath Exceeded <hi>Sodom</hi> in Wickedneſs. The Lord is very <hi>Angry</hi> with a great part of its Inhabitants, and his <hi>Vengeance</hi> is nigh to come upon them. <hi>Wo unto you Whoremongers, Drunkards, Gluttons, Swearers, Curſers, Blaſphemers, Cheaters,</hi> and <hi>Idolaters! Wo unto you, Proud, Wanton,</hi> and <hi>Prophane, Vain Perſons! Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Mountebanks, Stage-Players, Bear-baiters, Gameſters,</hi> and all manner of <hi>Abominable Workers,</hi> and you that Build up <hi>Towers, Scaffolds,</hi> and <hi>Vain Heatheniſh Repreſentations</hi> and <hi>ſuch like;</hi> and make and garniſh <hi>Images,</hi> to draw peoples minds after <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and for your <hi>Curſed Gain</hi> and <hi>Luſts,</hi> in pretence of <hi>Honouring your King.</hi> Oh! How are people drawn into <hi>Gazing</hi> and <hi>Wondring</hi> after theſe <hi>Abominations!</hi> It grieveth the Righteous Soul to behold ſuch great <hi>Wickedneſs!</hi> Oh! You <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Abominable Workers,</hi> and <hi>Devourers</hi> of the Creation! The Lord God will meet with you in a time when ye are little aware of Him, He'l <hi>Stain your Pride, Vain Glory</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and give you your Portion amongſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers</hi> (except you ſpeedily Repent) and your <hi>Abettors, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> and <hi>Helpers forward</hi> of ſuch Ungodlineſs (that do it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41404:12"/>
and <hi>Delighters</hi> therein, The Lord will not acquit you, He'l ſmite you for theſe things, and that right ſoon. Oh! Ye, <hi>Idolatrous people,</hi> Do you think, that the Lord God of Pitty and Patience, ſuffered your King to Hide himſelf from his Enemies <hi>in an Oake,</hi> for that end, that ye might <hi>Devour</hi> his Creatures in make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Idol of it?</hi> Is this the uſe you make of that which you ſay was <hi>Gods Mercy</hi> towards you? Is not this the way to turn thoſe things, that might have been Mercies to you, into Plagues and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Oh! How do you daily <hi>provoke</hi> the Lord againſt <hi>Your ſelves,</hi> and your <hi>King?</hi> Oh! You <hi>wicked Workers,</hi> How dare you make <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations</hi> of <hi>Deſtruction</hi> and <hi>Ruine?</hi> How dare you make a Sport of ſuch things? Verily, <hi>your provocations</hi> are great, wherewith <hi>you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke</hi> the <hi>Juſt God;</hi> And it will be Juſt with him to bring <hi>Ruine, Deſolation,</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> upon <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>City;</hi> Verily, great is the Judgment that is nigh you, and your ſins draw it on you apace. Do you think that the Lord caſt out <hi>Back-ſliders, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithful men,</hi> to ſet up and eſtabliſh <hi>Idolaters</hi> and open <hi>Prophane perſons?</hi> Nay ſurely: Therefore <hi>Tremble</hi> ye <hi>Wicked Workers,</hi> and <hi>Howle</hi> ye <hi>Prophane Idolaters,</hi> for the <hi>Mighty</hi> and <hi>Terrible day</hi> of the Lord <hi>is near</hi> to break out upon you. Thus ſaith the Lord God, I'le <hi>Scatter,</hi> I'le <hi>Scatter,</hi> I'le <hi>Split, Divide,</hi> and <hi>Separate:</hi> I'le <hi>Break</hi> and <hi>Daſh</hi> to <hi>Pieces, and none ſhall be able to Gather, Bind up, or Joyn together: For mine Anger is kindled, and my Jealouſie ſhall burn till I have devoured mine Enemies,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Therefore ye people of <hi>England</hi> (that yet live in wickedneſs) who have not wholly ſinned out the day of your <hi>Viſitation,</hi> To you I now ſpeak; you that feel the Lord yet ſtriving with you; O <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, return</hi> ſpeedily unto the Manifeſtation of his Spirit, whereby he ſtrives with you, to ſhew you your <hi>Abominations,</hi> and to draw and lead you out of the ſame; O be not ſtill <hi>Stiff-necked,</hi> but hearken to the Word of the Lord which ſheweth you the thoughts and Intents of your Hearts, and hearken and be obedient to the Call thereof, that ſo by its power you may <hi>Haſten</hi> out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> both <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Old, Rich</hi> and <hi>Poor, High</hi> and <hi>Low, Noble</hi> or <hi>Ignoble, Profeſſor</hi> or <hi>Profane,</hi> who yet are there; For the Lords Controverſie is great with <hi>Babylon</hi> her <hi>Merchants,</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> and he will not much longer ſpare, but he will ſuddenly ſmite, and none ſhall be able to hinder his ſtroak: Yea, yea he will <hi>wound</hi> and none ſhall be able
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41404:13"/>
               <hi>to heal;</hi> For the <hi>meaſure</hi> of her <hi>Iniquities, Idolatries,</hi> and <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> are <hi>nigh full,</hi> and the Wine of her Fornications, hath cauſed the Fatts to overflow, and ſhe is come up into remembrance before the Lord, the Juſt God, who will Plague her and all her <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants</hi> according to their <hi>Abominations,</hi> whereby they have grievouſly provoked <hi>Him,</hi> Therefore, come out of her, whilſt Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Time is offered, leſt you periſh with her in her Judgments, which the Lord is Strongly and Swiftly bringing upon her.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> A day of <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Calamity</hi> is come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon many of thy <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> I have long been ſenſible of it; even a day of ſuch <hi>Breaking, Confuſion</hi> and <hi>Judgement,</hi> as hath not been <hi>for a long ſpace;</hi> For thy People have wearied out the Lord <hi>with their iniquities</hi> and grieved his holy Spirit <hi>with their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,</hi> days without number.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> The Lord hath a <hi>precious</hi> and <hi>Holy Seed</hi> in thee; Yea, He hath a <hi>Remnant,</hi> which he hath raiſed by his Power to, &amp; for himſelf, which are exceeding precious in his ſight; and theſe a great part of thine Inhabitants have <hi>Shamefully entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>grievouſly oppreſſed,</hi> and <hi>perſecuted;</hi> And they have <hi>patiently</hi> born the ſame, and have laboured in the Life of <hi>Innocency,</hi> and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Emanuel,</hi> to Inform thy <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>People</hi> in the Things that are <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> and have ſhewn them the <hi>Wayes</hi> which have, and do <hi>Diſpleaſe</hi> the Lord, and have Exhorted and Warned the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, Time after Time: But notwithſtanding their <hi>Doctrine, Lives,</hi> and <hi>Converſations</hi> have manifeſted their <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs</hi> of <hi>Heart</hi> before God and Man, yet have many of thy <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>People, Oppreſſed</hi> them <hi>more</hi> and <hi>more;</hi> Some <hi>Spoiling their Goods,</hi> others <hi>Impriſoning their Bodies,</hi> in filthy <hi>Holes</hi> and <hi>Dungeons,</hi> till Several of them have Sealed their Teſtimony for the Lord with <hi>their Blood,</hi> which cryeth <hi>for Vengeance</hi> in the Ears of the Almighty, and the Lord hath heard the Cry thereof, and hath looked down and beheld the <hi>Actings</hi> of the Sons of men, and he is near to Viſit; Yea, the Lord hath <hi>beheld,</hi> and doth <hi>behold,</hi> the Snares that have been, and are laid for the Innocent, who have no other Helper but him alone; and therefore they have Commited their Cauſe unto him who ſhall bring it to paſs; Yea, he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Notice, how ſeveral of thy <hi>Rulers</hi> have combin'd together, and endeavoured <hi>to Force</hi> his <hi>Babes</hi> to Violate his Royal Law, and to Break his Command (who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all</hi>) to Uphold and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41404:13"/>
Obey theirs, which is Contrary to his; Yea, He hath taken notice of the <hi>Cruel Sufferings,</hi> and great <hi>Temptations</hi> of his People who, many of them, are <hi>yet Impriſoned,</hi> and both their <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> threatned to be deſtroyed (by ſome evil Men) if they will not break the Royal Law and Commandment of Chriſt, which he hath placed in their hearts to Obey &amp; Do. Oh! The Lord hath ſeen the <hi>Partiality</hi> and <hi>evil Intents</hi> of ſeveral of the <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of this Land, who have had Power to let the Innocent go free, and yet keep many of his <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> (many of which have outward Eſtates) Priſoners in many places; although they have no more againſt them, than againſt thoſe whom they have turned forth, which is nothing elſe but for their Obeying the Command of Chriſt in them, (who this day ſaith unto his People, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> as he ſaid to his Diſciples formerly) and for <hi>meeting together,</hi> and <hi>Speaking</hi> and <hi>Praying</hi> in his Name, for the <hi>Edifying, Comforting</hi> and <hi>Building up one another in their moſt holy Faith.</hi> The Lord hath alſo taken notice, that when ſome of the Rulers might Relieve <hi>the Innocent,</hi> and let <hi>the Oppreſſed go free,</hi> they will not; and then to cover themſelves, they wil ſay, <hi>They cannot act contrary to the Law.</hi> But when a Ruler will act that which he hath no Law for, he can then plead <hi>a Prerogative Royal for that:</hi> and thus are the innocent Lambs of Chriſt made a Prey upon.</p>
            <p>Oh! the <hi>Oppresſions</hi> of his People, and others, are great this day in thee, O Land; and the Crying of the <hi>Fatherleſs,</hi> the <hi>Widows</hi> and the <hi>Needy</hi> is come up before the Lord God of Compaſſion, who will thorowly plead the Cauſe of his People, and the Poor and Needy of the Land.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> I have oft heard and treaſured up what the Lord hath ſaid in me, concerning thy Inhabitants; but now muſt I declare it in the Appointed Seaſon, Thus hath the Lord ſpoken in me for a long time, concerning thy Inhabitants, ſaying, <hi>The People are <hi>too many,</hi> the People are <hi>too many;</hi> I will <hi>thin them,</hi> I will <hi>thin them:</hi>
               </hi> [Mark] that is, <hi>He will make them <hi>fewer,</hi>
               </hi> for they cumber the Ground. And the ſpirit of the Lord hath oft ſignified unto me, for a long time, <hi>That an <hi>Over-flowing Scourge,</hi>
               </hi> yea, <hi>even an exceeding <hi>great</hi> and <hi>terrible Iudgment</hi> is to come upon thee, O Land!</hi> and that many in thee <hi>ſhall fall</hi> and be <hi>taken away</hi> in the Judgment; and the Spirit of the Lord ſignifieth unto me, that the <hi>time draweth nigh,</hi> and that the <hi>Decree</hi> of the Lord is ſo firm, that though ſome of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41404:14"/>
Lords Children &amp; Prophets could appear ſo, as to ſtand in the <hi>Gap,</hi> yet ſhould not that alter his Decree, only in the Righteouſneſs of the Lamb they ſhall be hid &amp; ſaved from his Wrath, what ever may be done to any of their Bodies; but his fierce Wrath &amp; Indignation ſhall be poured forth upon the Ungodly, and a <hi>great Deſolation</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> ſhall there be; for he will <hi>overturn</hi> and <hi>overturn,</hi> till he hath <hi>diſ-throned</hi> &amp; <hi>thrown down</hi> the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> &amp; <hi>exalted</hi> &amp; <hi>eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> the Kingdom of his <hi>dear Son,</hi> over all the Kingdoms of the world; and the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Dominion,</hi> and the Greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole. Heaven ſhall be given to the Holy People, the Sints of the Moſt High, <hi>whoſe Kingdom is an Everlaſting Kingdom,</hi> and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him, who is King of Saints.</p>
            <p>Behold, ye <hi>Deſpiſers,</hi> and <hi>Wonder!</hi> This is the Work which the Lord will accompliſh by his own Power, though you will in no wiſe believe it; but you ſhall feel, even both <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>Prophane,</hi> that the Lord is able to bring to paſſe the thing that is in his heart.</p>
            <p>And you who now think <hi>to ſet up</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> your <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and to live in <hi>Prophaneſs</hi> without <hi>control;</hi> and you who appear <hi>ſo hot</hi> againſt ſome of theſe things, and labour to ſtop and pull them down (mark) that you might ſet up and eſtabliſh your own <hi>Hypocritical <hi>Will-Worſhip</hi>
               </hi> in another <hi>dark dead Form, I will fruſtrare <hi>you both,</hi>
               </hi> ſaith the Lord God, and <hi>you ſhall grind and waſte <hi>one</hi> againſt <hi>another,</hi> as the</hi> upper <hi>and</hi> nether <hi>Milſtone; And I will pluck out from you, and preſerve a holy Seed, beyond expectation;</hi> and I will <hi>be avenged on you</hi> for that which you have already <hi>bruiſed,</hi> or ſhall yet <hi>bruiſe</hi> [mark] And I will <hi>hurry</hi> and <hi>hurl <hi>you round</hi>
               </hi> with a mighty <hi>Stream;</hi> for the Waters ſhall <hi>roar</hi> and <hi>ſwell:</hi> And after I have executed <hi>my venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> upon the <hi>Rebellious</hi> and <hi>Treacherous Dealers,</hi> I will then bring forth the <hi>Remnant</hi> of my Holy Seed, which ſhall be <hi>preſerved</hi> from their <hi>Fury,</hi> and they ſhall ſpread over all, in my Life, Power, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Wiſdom, wherein they ſhall ſtand in Dominion; Yea, and they ſhall rule the Earth in <hi>Mercy, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>true Judgement;</hi> and they ſhall <hi>forgive</hi> and <hi>love their Enemies</hi> (as they do at this day) and do the thing that is <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>good</hi> unto all, without <hi>reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> yea, they ſhall ſeek the good of the whole Creation in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>true love</hi> and <hi>ſelf-denial;</hi> for the Spirit of <hi>Love, Meekneſs, Healing</hi> and <hi>Reſtoring</hi> ſhall mightily fill their tender Bowels, and my Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings ſhall fill their Dwelling-place, and the Earth, for their ſakes:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41404:14"/>
theſe things will I accompliſh by my own Power, and in my own time, ſaith the Lord God.</p>
            <p>But although theſe things, touching the holy Remnant, ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be fulfilled in their Seaſon, Yet before they be fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, great will be the Tryals of many of the Righteous, and there will be <hi>great Judgments</hi> executed in thee, O Land, by Him who oft-times maketh <hi>a fruitful Land barren,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of them that dwell therein; and Juſt will it be with Him to deal ſo with thee, becauſe of the <hi>great wickedneſs</hi> of the greateſt part of thy Inhabitants, who are departed and ſeparated from the Spirit of Mercy, Love, Compaſſion and Healing, and are labouring to <hi>Devour, Oppreſs,</hi> and <hi>Deſtroy</hi> one another, and the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> There is alſo a People in thee who are come to ſee <hi>the Great <hi>Idolatry</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> which many are now ſtriving to revive and <hi>ſet up</hi> in thee; yea, there is a People in thee, which ſee and believe that the Worſhip which is now a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up, with the <hi>Vain <hi>Muſick, Altars, Maſs</hi>
               </hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the fooliſh needleſs <hi>Garments <hi>of the</hi> Prieſts,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Popiſh ſtuff,</hi> that theſe things are <hi>Idolatry, Folly</hi> and <hi>Vanity, <hi>and but a mocking of God;</hi>
               </hi> and yet ſome of theſe People will run after this <hi>Vain Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> for <hi>ſelf-ends, ſlaviſh fear,</hi> and to keep themſelves in eſteem with, or amongſt thoſe who plead for it: And others there are in thee, who inſtead of being ſorrowful for ſuch Abominations and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, or reproving the Practicers thereof in the ſolid, ſeaſoned, ſavoury Life and holy Dread of the Lord God, they write and ſpeak <hi>ſcoffingly</hi> of thoſe things, even to the ſtirring up one of another into <hi>vain Laughter,</hi> and ſo make a ſport of others <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and this grieveth the Spirit of the Lord alſo, and doth not convince, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate and harden thoſe that are zealous for their <hi>blind Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are alſo a great number of <hi>brittle, fiery, raſh, unſatisfied people</hi> in thee, O Land, who are as <hi>unſtable</hi> as Water, and theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt the Light, not knowing the way of it, becauſe they abide not in the path thereof, they are <hi>reſtleſs, rouling,</hi> and <hi>raging</hi> oft-times like the Sea; One time they will have a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and cry out, <hi>They ſhall govern</hi> and <hi>heal them;</hi> and when they have gotten them, in a ſhort time they grow weary of them: And then another time, they will cry out for <hi>a King,</hi> and ſay, <hi>He ſhall heal them,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41404:15"/>
               <hi>make up their Breaches:</hi> But theſe people are not long of one mind, for they are much like the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who ſpent their time in little elſe but either <hi>to tell</hi> or <hi>to hear of ſome New thing:</hi> Theſe People alſo are like mighty Tydes in thy Chanels, <hi>O England,</hi> which one while run with <hi>Violence,</hi> driving all <hi>unſetled, light, unfixed</hi> things <hi>one way,</hi> and ſhortly after run with as much violence the contrary way: Therefore in a miſerable condition are thoſe Rulers whoſe ſtrength is in ſuch a People! And untill Rulers come to be ſetled, and fixed in Him who is the <hi>Rock of Ages,</hi> and ſingly to rule in, and for Him, whom the Winds and the Seas obey, who maketh the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſtand on heaps and divided them hither and thither; and altereth the natural courſe of <hi>Tydes</hi> as he pleaſeth (as he hath done thine of late, to ſhew thee the Figure of the People) they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſafe, neither will the People be ſtill'd long together; but there will be <hi>Swellings, Ragings, Overflowings, ſore Breakings and Ruines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! that the <hi>foregoing Rulers</hi> would have been perſwaded to have Received Him for their Teacher, who Ruleth in the Kingdoms of Men, then ſhould they not onely have ſeen, what the Lord caſt out others before them for, but they ſhould have been taught how to have denied all thoſe things which the <hi>Lord</hi> was angry with others for, and they ſhould have received Power to have abſtained from the ſame; but they would not hear and obey the Lord, nor his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and therefore were they caſt out alſo.</p>
            <p>And therefore, O! that the <hi>Rulers</hi> that now are, would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (whilſt they have their Day) by the Lord and his Servants, to receive the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to be their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> and then they ſhould not onely ſee for <hi>what cauſe</hi> the Lord caſt them out, and <hi>others</hi> in their Age, but they ſhould be taught to <hi>deny</hi> and <hi>forſake</hi> all thoſe <hi>things</hi> which God was angry with them, and others for, and they ſhould receive Power to do thoſe things, which they and others before them left undone; But alas! How few are there that will <hi>Hear, Regard,</hi> and <hi>Obey</hi> the Prince of Life and his Followers, and therefore is Deſolation coming as a mighty Flood, which none ſhall be able to ſtop.</p>
            <p>Now all People, in what Sect or Opinion ſoever, in whom there are any true <hi>Breathings</hi> and <hi>Deſires</hi> after the Lord, and the way of his Holines, <hi>Fear not,</hi> neither <hi>be diſmaid,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Rage</hi> that you may yet ſee the Waters of the Land in, and becauſe of the <hi>Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> of the People; But <hi>ſtand ſtill</hi> in that Life which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41404:15"/>
               <hi>Breathings</hi> and <hi>Thirſtings <hi>in you</hi>
               </hi> after the Lord, that you may come to ſee and feel his <hi>Salvation,</hi> and that you may be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into that <hi>Patience, Meekedneſs, Contendedneſs, Reſt, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> which many of the dear Lambs and Children of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are gathered into, wherein they lye down, and none can make them afraid, though their Bodies and Eſtates be oppreſſed and abuſed. Oh! <hi>Stick not, Stick not</hi> in your <hi>Formes</hi> without <hi>Power,</hi> neither Flee the Croſs, any longer; but wait in the True <hi>Simplicity,</hi> to feel God's hand of Tender Love, which he reacheth forth to, and manifeſteth <hi>in you,</hi> to lead and guide your minds into his Pure Worſhip, which is in the Spirit and in the Truth. Oh People! This is the Worſhip that he will ſet up. He will be <hi>LORD</hi> and <hi>LAW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIVER</hi> in the Conſciences of his People, and thoſe that will not be content that <hi>EMMAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL</hi> ſhould <hi>Reign</hi> over them, he will ſlay them with the <hi>Sword</hi> of the <hi>Spirit, <hi>The Words of his Mouth.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! <hi>Hearken, hearken</hi> a little, and <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> that you may hear the voice of the true Shepherd <hi>in your own Hearts,</hi> who calleth for Truth in the Inward Parts, and he will diſcover what lodgeth <hi>Within,</hi> and He will ſhew you the Way wherein you ſhould walk, and he will let you ſee what the Croſs is unto, and He will teach you when you are nlone in your Beds, or where-ever you are; if you will receive Him who gives you Life and Breath, whoſe <hi>gentle Reproofes</hi> and <hi>Inſtructions</hi> are the Way of Life.</p>
            <p>Therefore you in whom the <hi>Breathings</hi> and <hi>Deſires</hi> after the <hi>Lord</hi> are; Conſult not with <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> neither reaſon againſt the <hi>Croſs,</hi> but ſubmit to every Appearance of Gods Power in you, which appeareth to Crucifie the Fleſhly Birth and Nature; which hath ſtood, and doth ſtand in Rebellion and Enmity againſt the Pure and Precious Life, and Requirings of the Lamb of God, that ſo that Mind which is at Enmity againſt God, and that Nature in <hi>you,</hi> which is diſobedient to his Commands in Spirit, may come to be Crucified, that ſo there may be a Change inwardly felt and witneſſed, by the working of the mighty Power of Chriſt in your Inward parts; and then the <hi>Deſires</hi> and <hi>Breathings</hi> which are Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in you after <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> they will be ſtrengthened, and the <hi>Teachings</hi> of the Almighty will be Truly known, and you believing in the Power, you will receive Power to obey and Practiſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41404:16"/>
the Lord ſhall make known unto you by his Spirit to be his Will and Requirings.</p>
            <p>Oh People! Let the <hi>Dread</hi> of the Lord <hi>Seize upon your Spirits,</hi> in this the Day of his Power, wherein he is <hi>Trying, Sifting</hi> and <hi>winnow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the Nations, and wait to feel that Life ariſe <hi>within you,</hi> which beareth <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt <hi>all evil <hi>within</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>without;</hi> that ſo yee may become more and more acquainted with the <hi>Teachings, Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and <hi>Leadings thereof,</hi> that thereby you may be drawn and led out of thoſe things which have kept your Souls in the Death, and hindred you from enjoying the Pure Peace of God. And this know and conſider; that all that come to witneſs their Souls raiſed out of Death, and brought to enjoy the Peace of God, they muſt Believe in the Life of the Quickning Spirit, <hi>which is the Second Adam, the Lord from Heaven,</hi> who <hi>for Sin</hi> Condemneth <hi>Sin in the Fleſh,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the <hi>Inward Parts</hi> of man, to work <hi>out ſin</hi> and <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> (which hath Separated from God) and ſo to make clean the heart and inſide of male and female.</p>
            <p>Oh People! This is the Work of Chriſt the Son of God, even <hi>to make <hi>manifeſt</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> the <hi>works of the Devil,</hi> and ſo to reconcile man unto God, by the Virtue of his <hi>own Life,</hi> which he gave <hi>a Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> for many; and bleſſed are all thoſe that believe in the Life of the Son of God, and feel &amp; know it <hi>manifeſted <hi>in their mortal fleſh:</hi>
               </hi> for they ſhall witneſs the Power of it to make all things new, and ſo their Souls will come up in the hand of God, and his Peace will be Received and Enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Oh people! <hi>Wait</hi> to know, and feel this Work of Chriſt <hi>within you,</hi> that ſo you may be made able to ſtand in the Judgment, and to Endure the Tryal, and that you may be Hid from the Wrath of the Lamb, which is nigh to come upon the <hi>Rebellious.</hi> Oh! Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, Thoſe that are his Followers, they come throw <hi>many tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations,</hi> and their <hi>overcoming</hi> their Enemies is <hi>by his Blood,</hi> not by <hi>a talk of it,</hi> but by <hi>the Virtue</hi> and <hi>power of it</hi> ſprinkled <hi>in their Hearts,</hi> which waſheth and maketh them White, Clean, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fault before God. Oh People my <hi>Bowels yearn!</hi> my <hi>Bowels yearn</hi> towards you! whoſe <hi>Deſires</hi> in any meaſure, are after the Lord: O that you would now Return with all your hearts unto Him, and obey the Voice of his Power <hi>in you;</hi> then ſhould you be made able to ſtand, and endure the fiery Trial which is come and coming. Oh! the Day <hi>haſtens</hi> wherein all <hi>Profeſſion</hi> that is not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41404:16"/>
grounded in the Life and Power of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſhew of it be) it will be ſo ſhaken, that an utter Blaſting and withering ſhall come upon it; and for that cauſe the Lord doth, and will yet ſuffer great Trials to come, both upon the <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi> of his Name; that ſo his <hi>Children</hi> [the <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi>] may be manifeſted unto all, and diſcerned from all that are but <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> though never ſo fair and ſeemingly Covered; For all Coverings but what is of the Power and Spirit it ſelf, ſhall be too Narrow; and all that are not Covered with the Spirit and Power of <hi>Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> their Shame and Nakedneſs ſhall appear more and more. This is the Teſtimony which the Spirit &amp; Word of Truth giveth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear,</hi> before the day of his Viſitation be wholly paſt, and the things belonging to his Peace be hid from his Eyes: For <hi>yet a little while and the Voice ſhall be, <hi>He that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill;</hi> For the Spirit of the Lord ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with fleſh,</hi> but his <hi>Plagues</hi> and <hi>Indignation</hi> ſhall be poured out upon ſuch as will not be <hi>gathered</hi> in the Day of his <hi>Patience, long Forbearance,</hi> and <hi>Free-love;</hi> and He or She that Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth <hi>Father, Mother, Husband, Wife, Children, Houſe,</hi> or <hi>Land, Liberty, Honour,</hi> or <hi>any Thing</hi> more than <hi>the Life</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> ſhall be counted not worthy of him, and plainly manifeſted ſo to be: <hi>Read this who can; and he that can receive it, let him: For the Time draweth nigh that theſe Sayings muſt be fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi> the Younger.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Printed the 13. of the Second Moneth.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41404:17"/>
            <head>To the King, And both Houſes of PARLIAMENT, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MEddle not with my People, becauſe of their Conſcience to me, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them not out of the Nation, becauſe of their Conſcience; For, if you do, I will ſend my Plagues upon you; and you ſhall know that I am the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written in obedience to the Lord By his Servant, <hi>Geo. Biſhope.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Briſtol</hi> 
                  <date>the 25th of the 9th Month, 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41404:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
